A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, International Affairs, Office of the Program Director, Office Files of Shepard Forman FA625
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, International Affairs, Office of the Program Director, Office Files of Shepard Forman
1987-1996
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation
FA625
19.2 Cubic Feet
Biographical / Historical
Shepard Forman was Director of the Ford Foundation's International Affairs Program in 1991 and served in that position until 1995. The International Affairs Program supported activities that contribute to world peace, the establishment of global law and justice and the strengthening of international economics and development.
Scope and Contents
This collection is comprised of materials that document the daily activities of the Office of Program Director of the International Affairs Program. The records of the Program Director are significant because they document the development of programs from the point of view of Foundation officials and program staff. The President and Trustees of the Foundation offered input in program objectives and activities while Program staff developed new initiatives and implemented grant activity in the areas of human rights, health, and social welfare in Latin America, Asia, Africa and Eastern Europe. Activities documented in the files include creation of new program initiatives, preparation of financial materials, reports, and strategy papers that were presented to the Board of Trustees and documentation of task forces and study group activities. Trip files offer insight about the process of program development in overseas offices.
Arrangement
This collections is comprised of six series:
I. Background Files
II. Board of Trustees Meeting Materials
III. Chronological Files
IV. Interoffice Memoranda
V. Trip Files
VI. Recruitment Files
Separated Materials
Unpublished reports written by Ford Foundation staff and consultants were removed from the papers and transferred to the Ford Foundation Archives Reports Collection. A list of the titles of these reports is appended to this register.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files and officers papers were transferred to, and accessioned by, RAC beginning in 2011. Accessions continue as necessary.
Conditions Governing Access
Records more than 10 years old are open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
Biographical / Historical
Segment One: International Activities of the Ford Foundation: An Overview
The Foundation's aspiration to become a national and international philanthropy for the advancement of human welfare was first formally expressed in the seminal 1949 report of the Gaither Study Committee, Report of the Study for the Ford Foundation on Policy and Program (RAC Library, call letters 361.7 GAI ), which was commissioned by the Board of Trustees to chart the Foundation's future. Foundation Trustees launched Ford's international grantmaking activities in 1950 when they approved the committee's report and its embrace of peace, democracy, and freedom. Since then, the Foundation has tackled these goals using a variety of strategies and responding to changing contexts, from the Cold War to the 1989 fall of the Berlin Wall and beyond.
Toward the Foundation's aspiration‎al goal, "the establishment of peace", its international activities have comprised a wide range of conceptual approaches and focus areas. These include international affairs, international studies, international understanding, arms control and disarmament, international law, international economic concerns, and overseas development in nearly every region of the world. Three distinct periods emerge for the international grantmaking defined by external contextual changes and internal changes in Foundation leadership and structures: the expansion era of 1950-1965; the transition and restructuring years of 1966-1988; and the post-1989 shift away from Cold War dichotomies. During each of the distinct historical periods the consistent objectives were: 1) to ensure freedom and democracy in developed countries; 2) to foster education and international understanding in all countries; and 3) to contribute to the social, economic, and political development of less developed countries.
Biographical / Historical
Segment 4. Period Sketch - The Post-1989 Shift Away from Cold War Dichotomies
Between 1989 and 1991, dramatic changes in the external international conditions created a significantly different context for Ford Foundation's international activities both in the United States and overseas. In November, 1989, the Berlin Wall fell. In February 1990, in South Africa, Nelson Mandela was released from prison. In December 1991, the Soviet Union dissolved. As a consequence, the Cold War was over, Western Europe no longer had a special strategic role in the Foundation, and program-related activities in Eastern Europe and the former Soviet Union multiplied. The Foundation not only continued the earlier efforts to fund leadership in the region; from 1990-1994, Ford also spent $1 million on the training of newly-elected parliamentarians in Eastern Europe and the former USSR. By 1993, half of the funds for grantmaking related to the former Soviet bloc were going to in-country individuals and institutions.
In 1989, Thomas also instituted a major restructuring of the Foundation to fulfill his vision of "One Foundation." All programs were put into one division led by Vice President Susan Berresford. Carmichael joined the Institute of International Education to run a program on Soviet and Eastern European Affairs and then higher education in South Africa. All the Foundation grant programs - domestic and international - reported to Berresford: Africa and the Middle East (AME, formerly MEA), Asia (ASIA), Latin American and the Caribbean (LAC/OLAC), Human Rights and Governance (HRG), Education and Culture (EC), Program-Related Investments (PRI), and International Affairs (IA).
The change in South Africa opened up many new opportunities to work in partnership with a range of South Africa partners to promote and sustain the transition to democracy. The Foundation supported women's groups working on law, development and reproductive rights. It contributed, for example, to the groups working on the Women's Chatter in South Africa, resulting in the adoption in 1994 of the first constitution anywhere that specifically included sections on women's rights.
During the 1990s, the promising political changes in African countries and elsewhere provided a positive perspective to counteract the continuing economic constraints facing the Foundation and the rising debt in developing countries. Both to reinforce local democratic initiatives and to address its economic challenges, the Foundation's field offices across Africa and the developing world shifted their support toward the promotion of smaller scale community-based initiatives.
Thomas supported work on arts and culture, not as a goal in itself, but, instead, as a means for promoting social justice, education, and human rights, both in the United States and in developing countries. At the same time, while reducing support for cultural institutions in the United States, such institutions received support overseas to preserve and celebrate national and local cultural heritages. While in South Africa, for example, the Foundation provided support for Johannesburg anti-apartheid theatre groups, in West Africa it funded for nearly two decades a program to preserve and make accessible cultural heritage by expand the training of museum leaders and strengthening museum exhibit and outreach capabilities.
In the early 1990s, the Foundation through its India office helped establish an independent foundation to enhance sustainability in the arts community. Ford envisioned new opportunities for cultural institution to rely on local resources focus on new forms of creativity and encourage young artists, in particular. Similar to the Indian effort, the Ford office in Egypt in 1993 provided support for an arts-focused foundation.
When Susan Berresford became president in 1996, with a strong commitment to globalization as well as concern for the uncertainty it created, she reorganized the Foundation in to three large program themes that would inform grantmaking in the United States and developing countries: Assets with a focus on poverty, Peace and Social Justice on rights issues, and Education, Media, Arts and Culture to pull together related endeavors. She also created a separate communications program. Each program was led by a vice president. Berresford strongly reinforced the institutional and grantmaking goal of affirmative action, an organizational goal that had been initiated in the Bundy era.
She maintained significant support, domestically and internationally for women's issues. She endorsed and encouraged the worldwide meetings staff members and grantees to continue to hold joint meetings in order to create a greater sense of partnership and shared purpose. The more promising international situation enabled the Ford Foundation in 1996 to open an office in Russia (Moscow) and in Vietnam (Hanoi). Berresford encouraged the development of local and regional peace and security programs in developing countries. A regional security, peace, and cooperation program in India, for instance, focused on the work of civil society groups as an increasingly prominent regional interest in South Asia.
In this period, the Foundation gave renewed the prominence of arts and culture in the US and maintained the commitment in developing countries. By 2000, funding levels for the Education, Media, Arts and Culture division were approaching parity with the other two, Assets and Peace and Justice.
Berresford also encouraged each of the programs to hold worldwide meeting to promote cross-program and cross-national collaboration in fields such as human rights, income generation, cultural preservation, and building capacity in the arts and arts management. One persistent question of such initiatives. Toward that end, and building on the earlier experiences in India and Egypt, Berresford worked closely with her senior vice president, Barry Gaberman and other staff to establish new foundations at the local and national levels, particularly in developing countries. Gaberman had been at the foundation since 1973, starting as assistant to the representative in Indonesia. After serving in a number of different positions, by 1984, under Thomas, he served as deputy vice president in the U.S. and International Affairs program. After the 1989, Thomas and Berresford appointed him deputy vice president. 1996, Berresford appointed him senior vice president.
As the twentieth century came to a close, the economic conditions of the 1970s and 1980s that had resulted in so much global debt, with special impact on the developing world, were slowly turning around. Many countries were experiencing economic growth and burgeoning democratic initiatives. Not only was the global economic situation improving but the Foundation's assets were also growing. Consequently, the Foundation was in a strong position to bring attention to long-standing issues holding back developing countries. The grants programs addressed the pressing need both for advanced training of young- to mid-career adults living in marginalized and disadvantaged conditions along the equally, and for strengthening and building sustainability of universities across sub-Saharan Africa, along with enhancing broadband access for improved internet communications, promoting women in higher education, and strengthening postgraduate education.
Reacting to the tragedy of September 11, 2001, the Foundation provided immediate relief to affected local institutions in the United States. The Foundation also helped launch support a fund at the Institute of International Education to support scholars at risk in countries in conflict and under terrorist threats, especially in, but not limited to, the Middle East.
Biographical / Historical
Segment 4. Period Summary - The Post-1989 Shift Away from Cold War Dichotomies
Franklin Thomas's presidency, lasting until his retirement in 1995, was defined by a commitment to connect the Foundation's US and international activities around a few key themes. These themes were addressed through grants that created private sector partnerships, enhanced support for local community groups, and enlarged initiatives to promote human rights, with special attention to women's rights. Throughout Thomas's tenure, Ford staff reinforced his special commitment to bolstering marginalized communities and broadening access to the law and educational opportunity. The Ford Foundation led the way in building the fields of international security studies, arms control, human rights, and governance. Moreover, in this period, Ford was innovative in drawing together the fields of international cooperation and human rights into one program.
Susan Berresford in her tenure as president from 1996-1997 continued and expanded the activities she helped initiate under Thomas. She and her colleagues increased support for the arts and established a variety of major international collaborative efforts implementing the concept of one foundation. Ford staff in this period drew on the Foundation's time-tested grantmaking strategies (supporting individuals and new institutions as needed), while concentrating on under-addressed issues and underserved populations. With Berresford's encouragement, Foundation staff explicitly took into account the new global context, increasing opportunities for inclusion of disadvantaged populations in all of their activities.
- Background Files, 1989-1996; I
  Scope and Contents
  Series I, Background Files (1989-1996), is comprised of materials mostly created by Ford Foundation staff and consultants. The various types of materials include memos, handwritten notes, charts, spreadsheets, proposals, letters, reports and papers by FF staff with handwritten comments by Forman as well as summaries of awarded grants, site visits reports, and grant FAPs.
  - Japan, Foundation Work – In (Box 1 (SK #38695), Folder 1)
  - Joint Center for Political and Economic Studies Williams – Hold for meeting (Box 1 (SK #38695), Folder 2)
  - Latin American Human Rights (Box 1 (SK #38695), Folder 3)
  - Lawyers Committee for Human Rights (Box 1 (SK #38695), Folder 4)
  - Kaiser, Paul (Box 1 (SK #38695), Folder 5)
  - Meyer, Jack – Economic & Social Research (Box 1 (SK #38695), Folder 6)
  - Mid-Decade Review (Background) (Box 1 (SK #38695), Folder 7)
  - Harold Richmau (Box 1 (SK #38695), Folder 8)
  - Mid-Decade Review / International Affairs (IA) (Box 1 (SK #38695), Folder 9)
  - Mid-Decade Review / International Affairs (IA) (Box 1 (SK #38695), Folder 10)
  - Mozambique (Box 1 (SK #38695), Folder 11)
  - National Institute for Dispute Resolution (NIDR) (Box 1 (SK #38695), Folder 12)
  - NCAP (Box 1 (SK #38695), Folder 13)
  - National Museum of the American Indian (Box 1 (SK #38695), Folder 14)
  - Peace and Security Program, 1992 December (Box 1 (SK #38695), Folder 15)
  - Public Radio International (PRI) (Box 1 (SK #38695), Folder 16)
  - Sharpe, Ken – Consulting on Central America (Box 1 (SK #38695), Folder 17)
  - SIPI (Box 1 (SK #38695), Folder 18)
  - Social Science Research Council (hold for proposal) (Box 1 (SK #38695), Folder 19)
  - Social Welfare/Eastern Europe (Box 1 (SK #38695), Folder 20)
  - Syria (Box 1 (SK #38695), Folder 21)
  - Somalia (Box 1 (SK #38695), Folder 22)
  - Sovereignty and Humanitarian Intervention (Box 1 (SK #38695), Folder 23)
  - Spencer – Visit to Eastern Europe (Box 1 (SK #38695), Folder 24)
  - Syria (Box 1 (SK #38695), Folder 25)
  - Terrorism (Box 1 (SK #38695), Folder 26)
  - Danilo Turk (Box 1 (SK #38695), Folder 27)
  - U.N.A. Evaluation (Box 1 (SK #38695), Folder 28)
  - U.N. Meeting – SF Notes, 1992 April 7 (Box 1 (SK #38695), Folder 29)
  - U.S. Foreign Policy (Box 1 (SK #38695), Folder 30)
  - Urban Opportunities Project Meeting, 1991 October 30 (Box 1 (SK #38695), Folder 31)
  - Wilson Center Report Nacht/Goodman/Trebat (Box 1 (SK #38695), Folder 32)
  - Social Summit Journey Papers (Box 1 (SK #38695), Folder 33)
  - ASIL Evaluation (Box 2 (SK #38699), Folder 1)
  - ASIL (Box 2 (SK #38699), Folder 2)
  - Jorg Baldauf Chron (Box 2 (SK #38699), Folder 3)
  - Salih Booker (Box 2 (SK #38699), Folder 4)
  - Bosnian Refugee File (Box 2 (SK #38699), Folder 5)
  - Brookings Affirmative Action Background (Box 2 (SK #38699), Folder 6)
  - Buffalo, U. of/Andras Sajo (Box 2 (SK #38699), Folder 7)
  - Cambridge, U. of – Global Security Program – 1991 (Box 2 (SK #38699), Folder 8)
  - Carnegie Endowment Moscow Center/Misc. (Box 2 (SK #38699), Folder 9)
  - Carnegie Endowment for Intl./Balkan Commission/M. Abramowitz (Box 2 (SK #38699), Folder 10)
  - Changing relations (Box 2 (SK #38699), Folder 11)
  - The Common Good – SF notes (Box 2 (SK #38699), Folder 12)
  - Council on Foreign Relations – General (Box 2 (SK #38699), Folder 13)
  - Cultural Survival, October 22, 1996 (Box 2 (SK #38699), Folder 14)
  - Cuba Task Force/CFR Cuba (Box 2 (SK #38699), Folder 15)
  - Eastern and Central Europe – Work of Private Foundation – Quiqtey Paper (Box 2 (SK #38699), Folder 16)
  - Goodman, Dr. Allen E., Georgetown U. Paper – "Diversity in Governance" (Box 2 (SK #38699), Folder 17)
  - Gorbackev Foundation (Box 2 (SK #38699), Folder 18)
  - G&PP – Program Papers for Trustees – 1985 (Box 2 (SK #38699), Folder 19)
  - Haiti (misc) (Box 2 (SK #38699), Folder 20)
  - Human Rights & Governance Rapporteur Notes – November 1991 meeting (Box 2 (SK #38699), Folder 21)
  - Human Rights Programming – Mexico City (Box 2 (SK #38699), Folder 22)
  - Institute for Human Services/TERC January 28, 1994 meeting (Box 2 (SK #38699), Folder 23)
  - Interviews (Box 2 (SK #38699), Folder 24)
  - Consultants' Reports – Miscellaneous, 1983 - 1993 (Box 3 (SK #39574), Folder 1)
  - Board of Trustees Meeting, September, 1993 – Background Materials and Correspondence, 1993 September (Box 3 (SK #39574), Folder 2)
  - Board of Trustees Meeting, September, 1993 – Draft Agendas and Logistics Schedules, 1993 September (Box 3 (SK #39574), Folder 3)
  - Biennium Background, 1995 - 1996 (Box 3 (SK #39574), Folder 4)
  - Biennium Background, 1994 - 1995 (Box 3 (SK #39574), Folder 5)
  - Biennial Program Review Background, 1995 (Box 3 (SK #39574), Folder 6)
  - USIAP Program Review, 1994 February (Box 3 (SK #39574), Folder 7)
  - E&C Program Review, 1993 December (Box 3 (SK #39574), Folder 8)
  - Joint Program Review, 1993 April (Box 3 (SK #39574), Folder 9)
  - USIAP Program Review, 1993 February (Box 3 (SK #39574), Folder 10)
  - Joint Program Review, 1992 May (Box 3 (SK #39574), Folder 11)
  - USIAP Program Review, 1992 February (Box 3 (SK #39574), Folder 12)
  - G&PP Program Review, 1992 January (Box 3 (SK #39574), Folder 13)
  - Joint Program Review, 1992 May (Box 3 (SK #39574), Folder 14)
  - Annual Report Materials, 1995 (Box 4 (SK #39576), Folder 1)
  - Annual Report Materials, 1994 (Box 4 (SK #39576), Folder 2)
  - Center for International Policy, 1996 (Box 4 (SK #39576), Folder 3)
  - Central American Initiative, 1994 - 1996 (Box 4 (SK #39576), Folder 4)
  - Communications, Office of, 1992 - 1995 (Box 4 (SK #39576), Folder 5)
  - Communications, Office of/Clinton Administration, 1993 (Box 4 (SK #39576), Folder 6)
  - Communications, Office of/Russia/EE Story, 1993 (Box 4 (SK #39576), Folder 7)
  - Council on Foreign Relations – Study Group "The Role of Regional Organizations in Peacekeeping and Conflict Resolution", 1994 (Box 4 (SK #39576), Folder 8)
  - Directors' Lunches – Misc. Material, 1989 - 1996 (Box 4 (SK #39576), Folder 9)
  - Directors' Retreat, 1995 July (Box 4 (SK #39576), Folder 10)
  - Education and Culture – Shared Programs/Int'l Studies/Area Studies—Background, 1993 - 1996 (Box 4 (SK #39576), Folder 11)
  - Ethnic conflict and the Protection of Minorities, 1992 - 1993 (Box 4 (SK #39576), Folder 12)
  - Executive Council on Foreign Diplomats, 1991 (Box 4 (SK #39576), Folder 13)
  - Fletcher School of Law and Diplomacy – background, 1991 (Box 4 (SK #39576), Folder 14)
  - Foreign Affairs – Fareed Zakaria, 1995 (Box 4 (SK #39576), Folder 15)
  - Shepard Forman – Misc., C.V., 1991 - 1996 (Box 4 (SK #39576), Folder 16)
  - Shepard Forman – 1993, 1994, 1995 Expense Reports (three folders), 1993 - 1995 (Box 4 (SK #39576), Folder 17)
  - Shepard Forman – Remittance Advice, 1991 - 1996 (Box 4 (SK #39576), Folder 18)
  - International Research and Exchanges Board, 1991 (Box 4 (SK #39576), Folder 19)
  - IAP Retreat & Meeting with Latin American Colleagues – Rapporteur Notes, 1992 February 22 - 25 (Box 4 (SK #39576), Folder 20)
  - IAP Retreat – Ashfield, MA – October 1992 – Rapporteur Notes, 1992 October (Box 4 (SK #39576), Folder 21)
  - IAP Worldwide Mtg/Lisbon, Portugal – November 1992/Background & Rapporteur Notes, 1992 November (Box 4 (SK #39576), Folder 22)
  - Ishtook Amendment Background, 1995 (Box 4 (SK #39576), Folder 23)
  - Letters from Law Schools re Public International Law Training, 1992 (Box 4 (SK #39576), Folder 24)
  - Flora Lewis – Correspondence, 1992 - 1993 (Box 5 (SK #39578), Folder 1)
  - Media Initiative background papers, 1988 - 1993 (Box 5 (SK #39578), Folder 2)
  - Miscellaneous articles and papers, 1990 - 1996 (Box 5 (SK #39578), Folder 3)
  - Mission Statement (Ford Foundation) Background, 1992 - 1994 (Box 5 (SK #39578), Folder 4)
  - Moscow Office background, 1994 - 1996 (Box 5 (SK #39578), Folder 5)
  - Moscow Office background, 1992 - 1994 (Box 5 (SK #39578), Folder 6)
  - Moscow Office Recruitment background, 1995 - 1996 (Box 5 (SK #39578), Folder 7)
  - Ivanka Needva Correspondence, 1993 (Box 5 (SK #39578), Folder 8)
  - Nigeria Consultation – M. McLean, 1995 (Box 5 (SK #39578), Folder 9)
  - Seamus O'Cleireacain – Program Paper, 1994 (Box 5 (SK #39578), Folder 10)
  - Anastasia Posadskaya – Correspondence re FF visit, 1993 (Box 5 (SK #39578), Folder 11)
  - Walter Raymond Correspondence, 1992 (Box 5 (SK #39578), Folder 12)
  - Rebeautification Committee (IAP) background, 1994 - 1995 (Box 5 (SK #39578), Folder 13)
  - Regional Security Background, 1991 (Box 5 (SK #39578), Folder 14)
  - Secretary's Good Offices Fund Background, 1991 - 1992 (Box 5 (SK #39578), Folder 15)
  - Soviet East European Study Group Materials, 1991 (Box 5 (SK #39578), Folder 16)
  - Sexual Harassment Workshop, 1992 (Box 5 (SK #39578), Folder 17)
  - Truman Awards for the Advancement of the Human Condition Correspondence, 1993 (Box 5 (SK #39578), Folder 18)
  - United Nations – General Materials, 1992 - 1995 (Box 5 (SK #39578), Folder 19)
  - United Nations Reform Publication Background – Childers/Urquhart, 1992 - 1994 (Box 5 (SK #39578), Folder 20)
  - USIAP Reserve Claims Material, 1989 - 1995 (Box 5 (SK #39578), Folder 21)
  - United Nations Status of Women Background Materials – Connor/Halliday, 1995 - 1996 (Box 5 (SK #39578), Folder 22)
  - Yale University/U.N. in the Second Half Century Correspondence, 1995 (Box 5 (SK #39578), Folder 23)
  - World Institute for the U.N. Background, 1991 (Box 5 (SK #39578), Folder 24)
- Board of Trustees Meeting Materials, 1987-1994; II